A Guide to the Papers of John Hay, 1872-1905
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Hay, 1872-1905
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7053-a
This collection consists of 35 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on December 17, 1963.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts of his poem "Night in Venice" and "Unto each man comes a day".
In his correspondence he discusses Lincoln, his commitment to peace and Mary E. Surratt's guilt; an article he has written on Elmer Ephraim Ellsworth; the Southern Historical Society Papers and their low editorial standards; his book "Bread-winners" for which he allows an Italian translation; the proofs of his book "Abraham Lincoln"; a small printing of his collected poems and his giving up poetry writing; his election to the Kauai Kodak Klub; Alfred Austin's "A Tale of True Love and Other Poems"; and Charles Elliott's "The Book of American Interiors." He also requests an autograph copy of "Stonewall Jackson's Way"; declines to purchase photographs of Lincoln; regrets social invitations; thanks Thomas Nast for a cartoon of "The Emperor Roosevelt and the Rough Rider Wilhelm" and criticizes [Sophia M. B.?] Herrick's notes on Lincoln. Two portraits of Hay are included.
Correspondents include Mr. Alden, Robert Coster, Mr. Cunningham, Richard Watson Gilder, E. S. Goodhue, [J. R.?] Osgood, John Williamson Palmer, Mr. Taylor, Mr. House, and H. D. Traill.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Poem beginning "Unto each man comes a day.. ." n.d., AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem: "Night in Venice" n.d., AmsS, 1 p.
- Letters
  - John Hay to Mr. Taylor 1872 Jan 5, ALS, 1 p.
    Expresses regret about "that engagement."
  - J. H. to Mrs. Mack 1872 Jan 11, AL, 1 p.
    Regrets he could not respond to her invitation.
  - J. H. to Cunningham 1876 Jun 20, ALS, 1 p.
    Thanks him for letter and remembrance. Mentions he has quit writing poetry.
  - J. H. to E. C. Hine 1881 Oct 6, ALS, 1 p.
    Thanks for dinner invitation, but will not be able to attend.
  - J. H. to Dr. J[ohn]; W[illiamson] Palmer 1886 Aug 17, ALS, 1 p., w/ typed transcript
    Asks for autograph copy of "Stonewall Jackson's Way," if J. W. P. is the author of it.
  - J. H. to Dr. J. W. Palmer 1886 Aug 24, ALS, 2 p., w/typed transcript
    Thanks J. W. P. for granting request; discusses "Southern Historical Society Papers." Adivses against buying the series because poorly edited.
  - J. H. to Richard Watson Gilder [1886 Nov 24], ALS, 1 p.
    Sends corrected proofs for Abraham Lincoln. Suggests subtitle "Lincoln in Congress." Thanks donor of Lincoln autograph.
  - J. H. to House [1890] Jan 16, ALS, 2 p.
    Wrote article on Ellsworth under pressure and has no feeling for it. Would like to write more on Ellsworth.
  - "The Author" [J. H.] to Mr [J. W.] Harper 1890 Jan 22, ALS, 1 p., w/ env.
    Asks if Bread-winners has earned anything. Requests half a dozen copies be sent him in Washington. W/AN 1890 Jan 22 J. W. Harper to W. Muller, to fill above order.
  - J. H. to Mr. [J. W. ?] Harper 1890 Mar 8, ALS, 1 p.
    Regrets cannot accept invitation because of previous engagment. Sends regards to William Dean Howells.
  - J. H. to Richard Watson Gilder 1894 Nov 23, ALS, 1 p.
    Indicates corrections for sonnet he submitted to R. W. G. Asks for proofs of same when printed.
  - J. H. to Samuel Sidney McClure 1895 Oct 31, ALS, 1 p., w/photo
    Requests a proof of the Ellsworth article before it is printed.
  - J. H. to "Dear Sir" 1897 Jul 19, ALS, 1 p.
    Has no objection to translation of Bread-winners into Italian, but will not put his name to the book.
  - H. D. Traill to J. H. 1898 Aug 22, ALS, 2 p.
    Accepts poem by Mr. [J. W. ?] Palmer for Literature(his London magazine).
  - J. H. to Mr. Palmer 1898 Aug 25, TLS, 1 p.
    Has sent P.'s poem to editor of Literature.
  - J. H. to E. S. Goodhue 1901 Apr 29, TLS, 1 p.
    Thanks for election as honorary member of the Kauai Kodak Klub. Signature probably not in J. H.'s hand.
  - J. H. to Harper & Brothers 1902 Apr 17, TLS, 1 p.
    Thanks for letter and copy of Alfred Austin's work, A Tale of True Love and Other Poems.
  - J. H. to Robert Coster 1903 Jan 27, TLS, 1 p.
    Will sign the photograph if sent to him.
  - J. H. to R. C. 1903 Jan 30, TLS, 1 p.
    Returns photograph, signed.
  - J. H. to R. C. 1903 Apr 29, TLS, 1 p.
    Returns photograph of President Lincoln; obliged for offer, but does not care to purchase it.
  - J. H. to R. C. 1903 Nov 17, TLS, 1 p.
    Returns miniture portrait of Lincoln. He is not collecting such things; refers him to Mr. Lambert of Philadelphia.
  - J. H. Dr. J. W. Palmer 1903 Dec 7, TLS, 1 p., w/typescript
    Has received enclosed poem, "Braddock." Sends copy congratulations; his verses are a sign of youth.
  - J. H. to Mr. Osgood n.y. Feb 14, ALS, 1 p.
    Asks for another copy of The Book of American Interiors; has promised one to a friend.
  - J. H. to Richard Watson Gilder n.y. Mar 7, ALS, 2 p.
    Denies stories critical of Lincoln. Insists on Lincoln's commitment to peace and union.
  - J. H. to Mr. Alden n.y. Jun 30, ALS, 1 p.
    Encloses a sonnet made for Alden.
  - J. H. to Richard Watson Gilder n.y. Oct 29, ALS, 1 p.
    Discusses extent of Mrs. Surratt's guilt in the Lincoln assassination.
  - J. H. to Miss King n.y. Dec 11, ALS, 4 p.
    Thanks for letter and photograph of his aunt Evelyn. Sends copy of all his verses; only a few copies have been printed, none of which are for sale.
  - J. H. to Richard Watson Gilder n.d., ALS, 1 p.
    Returns [Sophia M'Ilvaine Bledsoe ?] Herrick's notes re Lincoln. Questions her accuracy, and criticizes her memory of issues. Concludes that even intelligent women are careless.
- Miscellaneous
  - Autograph on fragment of document, with seal of Department of State 1880 Aug 28, Autograph
  - Proclaimation by Theodore Roosevelt on death of John Hay. 1905 Jul 3, Printed broadside
  - Autobiographical data for United Press Bureau n.d., Notes
    in hand of J. H. while Secretary of State, ca.1898-1905.
  - J. H., U.S. Secretary State, head and shoulders n.d., Photograph
  - Photograph of bust of J. H., by Augustus Saint-Gaudens n.d., Photograph